Everyone is using AI coding assistance
very differently. You'd be surprised how
large the spectrum is even for companies
that are using these tools to ship
production code. And the best
explanation I found for the different
ways we can use coding agents is from
Dan Shapiro. So in this blog post, the
five levels from spicy auto complete to
the dark factory. And it's really
important for you to understand the
level that you're currently at and what
you should be shooting for. And the
level that's best for you also changes
over time as you create a more
structured approach to AI coding. And so
in this video, I want to break down each
one of the levels in nice and simple for
you and help you understand where you
should be at right now. And I just want
to share some honest thoughts especially
on some of the last levels especially
with the dark factory. I see a lot of
companies go for this right now and I've
even built my own. But there are a lot
of downsides to the dark factory as
powerful as it is. And so we'll get into
the meat of that as well. All right, so
let's get right into the different
levels of AI coding. And this entire
article uses the analogy of driving a
vehicle cuz there's a company in 2013
that created the five levels of driving
automation. And it's very neat because
we can map each one of these levels
directly to how we interact with AI
coding assistants. How much are we
leaning on them versus keeping our hands
on the driver's wheel when we are
interacting with them and having them
create the code for us. And so level
number one is spicy auto complete. I
love this name by the way. And here
you're still writing every single line
of code yourself. You're just using the
coding agent as a reference tool or some
kind of enhanced search. So it's like a
smarter stack overflow. And so it never
has the final say. It doesn't get to
write a line of code, but you're
constantly leaning on it for how should
I architect this or how should I write
this function. And so it's like your
parents Volvo. So maybe even having
automatic transition. This is the most
manual you can possibly be. You have to
manage the car at a very fundamental
level. And so, you can see that it's
actually level zero because we're not
really having the coding agent do
anything for us. And so, then we get
into level one. And so, this is like the
coding intern. Or when you're driving a
car, you have cruise control. It's that
first level of autonomy where there's at
least one part of the car that's being
managed on your behalf. And so, here
your coding agent is going to write the
unimportant or boilerplate code. And so,
setting up your initial repository,
maybe installing packages, writing unit
tests, doing simple refactors, that kind
of thing. You're not leaning on it for
anything that takes true reasoning, but
you're still saving a good amount of
time here. And then level two takes us
to the junior developer. This is where
you really start to lean on the coding
agent or lean on the car to operate
pretty autonomously, but only in some
situations. So, when you're driving,
it's like you have autopilot on the
highway. But when you're actually
driving in the city and there's a lot of
turns and rules that need to be
followed, you can't trust it anymore.
So, it's a junior developer where you're
doing a lot of pair programming. You are
handing off a lot of the boring work,
but there still are going to be those
things where you don't trust it entirely
and you're driving the process very
manually. And there's a good chance that
this is where you are at right now.
Because if you don't have a very
established system for how to leverage
AI coding assistants and have them
evolve over time, and we'll talk about
that in a little bit, then you probably
don't trust it for every kind of task.
There are certain things where you think
it's just going to be better for you to
do it yourself, especially if you're
more technically inclined. And I do
really encourage you to get past level
two. So, when we start to talk about
level three here, this is where I really
want you to be. And so, it's easy to get
here because you're trusting it with the
easy stuff, like autopilot on the
highway. But when you really create a
system for planning and implementing and
validating, that's when you go into
level three, the developer. This is
where you get to the point where your
coding agent is writing a majority of
the code base, which is what it says
right here, but honestly, I would take
this a little bit further. When you get
to level three, and this is mostly where
I operate, this is where you're
delegating all of the coding to your
agent. And I myself haven't written a
single line of code for over a year now,
which is crazy to think because I've
spent years and years of my life writing
code every single day. And so, as an
engineer, it took a while to get to the
point where I had the system and built
the trust to get to level three. But
there's a good chance this is where you
should be. This is the sweet spot of
reliability and autonomy. Cuz as it
relates to driving a car, it's like a
Waymo with a safety driver. You're
letting the coding agent really go, or
you're letting the car do all the
driving, but you're still in the
driver's seat. You're still attentive,
you're still driving the process. And
so, what I like to say here for level
three is the only reason that we
delegate all the coding to the agent and
trust it to do that is because we're
sandwiching the implementation with a
lot of planning and a lot of validation
that we are very much a part of. And so,
you delegate all the coding, but you
still remain in the driver's seat. But
that starts to change once we get to
level four. This is the level where we
reach the engineering team. You're
handing off much larger sets of work for
the coding agent to knock out
autonomously. And so, you're still at
the helm, but you're sleeping for long
periods of time because we're letting
the agent rip through larger sets of
work based on something like an epic, a
PRD, or a spec. Level three is more like
each individual task. We're doing the
planning and validation with the coding
agent, but here we're just doing the
very high-level direction setting up
front, and then the validation at the
very end. Like a set of pull requests,
for example. And so, we're letting it
go, go, go based on a larger spec. And
so, it's not quite the dark factory.
We'll talk about this in just a second
where there's not even a driver's seat.
Like right like we still have control of
the system to an extent, but we're just
not doing that very often. And at this
level, this is where your reliability
really starts to tank until you have a
trusted and really well-established
workflow for AI coding going from idea
all the way to production. And it takes
a while to get there. That's why I
recommend you stay at level three or you
at least stay here for a long time
because you build up that system and
then you can start to make your coding
agent more autonomous. So really just
taking the system that you were more a
part of and then taking out the human in
the loop as you go to get to levels four
and five. And so I'll talk about in a
little bit what it actually takes to
create this system. What actually is a
system for AI coding, but first let's
talk about the dark factory for a bit.
So at level five, it really isn't even a
car anymore. Let me zoom in on this you
can see this image well. There is no
driver's wheel. We can't even take
control and grab the reins even if we
wanted to. Now there's still a console
in this vehicle, whatever it is, this
spaceship. So the console allows us to
still input our highest-level directions
possible, but yeah, we're not
controlling any of the development. And
so the way that a dark factory works is
your input is your spec, the large
document that outlines everything you
want to build. And what you get out of
the dark factory is shipped code. And so
that's probably the biggest difference
between level five and four. Level four,
you're not trusting the coding agent to
ship right to production, but in level
five, you actually are. And if that
sounds kind of scary, it should. And
that's why I'm saying you have to be
very careful when you get to this level
of autonomy. Cuz if there's one thing
you have described wrong in the spec or
the coding agent just make some kind of
incorrect assumption, that could lead to
dozens of shipped deployments that are
just botching what you wanted to
actually create. But in the end, the
dark factory is ideal. If your business
can get to the point where you have a
process where you can send in a spec and
get out shipped code, that, my friend,
is the dream. And we're starting to get
to the point where the dark factory is
becoming realistic. Now, I I want to be
very careful how I put this right now
because I don't want you to just reach
for the dark factory immediately. But, I
think that there is a possibility you
can get here with the current tooling
and LLMs we have available. And so, you
can probably jump to level three very
fast. I mean, that's what I teach on my
YouTube channel and in the Dynamis
community. Like, creating the system
where you're still in the loop for each
individual build, but you have quite a
bit of autonomy. You're delegating all
the coding to the agents. So, you start
here. This is where I want you to be.
And then, you take out the human in the
loop as you create that system where you
really trust that it understands your
code base and your workflows and things
are reliable.
And so, there are some companies that
are starting to come out of the woodwork
sharing how they do have a dark factory
that's actually running. StrongDM is one
example. I'll link to an article on that
in the description. A lot of other
companies aren't really documenting
anything like StrongDM, so it's just
some rumors that are starting to surface
of companies that are doing this
successfully. Even in the banking
industry, even when the code has to be
perfect when it's shipped to production.
So, it's definitely possible, but we
need the system to get there. And so,
with that, let's actually get into what
does a system for AI coding look like
and how do we build something that can
even take the form of the dark factory?
The sponsor of today's video is Sonar.
They're making big moves in the AI
coding space right now. The reality is
that these days AI is writing a huge
chunk of new code, and that, my friend,
is not slowing down. But, the problem is
traditional code reviews and quality
gates were never made for volume at this
speed. And so, bugs slip through and AI
errors compound on themselves and your
code base gets fragile quickly. That is
why Sonar has acquired Gitarr. Gitarr is
AI code review that actually fixes your
code. It's not just another agent you
throw at the problem, it's an entire
harness for validation, making your code
more reliable with full visibility as
well. The way that Gitarr works is you
connect it to any of your GitHub or
GitLab repositories and then as soon as
you open up a pull request, we can see
Gitarr here running a comprehensive code
review. And not only does it do the code
review but can also fix the issues that
it finds automatically as well. So right
here, it identified and fixed a SQL
injection vulnerability that I have in
this pull request. And the best part for
all of this is every single time it
makes a fix, it automatically validates
it against your CI. So it's just
increasing the reliability even more. It
even reads your CI failures for you. So
it can do things like dedupe your
errors, help you identify flaky tests,
and clean up your build and lint
failures not drowning in logs. And you
can see this is all very in line with
Sonar's agent-centric development life
cycle, a framework that's based on the
three pillars of guide, verify, and
solve. And Gitarr fits very well into
their verify pillar. And teams using
Sonar are 44% less likely to hit
production outages caused by AI
generated code. And it's not about
replacing your human judgment, it's just
a serious safety net under everything
your agent ships. And Gitarr has a
14-day free pro trial, no credit card
required. I'll link to it in the
description. All right, so I put a lot
of time into thinking about how I can
quickly describe what a system is to you
for AI coding. And I want to be concise
because that's really not the point of
this video to dive super deep into the
weeds of system engineering or context
engineering, but I wanted to give you an
idea of what you're going to be creating
and evolving to trust your coding agent
to be more autonomous over time. And so
I decided to pull from the Dynamis
Agentic Coding Course. So, taking a
couple of the things that I have there
and just showing it really fast. And so,
I want to start by talking about the AI
layer because these are the different
components that you build on top of your
coding agent. Things like your rules and
skills. So, your coding agent
understands your conventions, your
context of your code base, and your
workflows. And when you think about
harness engineering, which is building
the system for AI coding, it really
starts at layer zero with the tool that
you pick. So, you don't control this,
but you get to pick the coding agent.
And the coding agent, it really is a
harness because it wraps the large
language model with the tools and
instructions to make it operate as an AI
coding assistant. And then we build the
layer on top. This is what we control
because we wrap the coding agent that it
itself wraps the LLM to provide a
context not on how to be an AI coding
assistant, but how we want it to be a
coding agent specifically on our code
base, with our workflows. And so,
there's really six components that we're
building up here. We create our rules.
These are the conventions we want our
coding agent to follow. We have our sub
agents, how we want to delegate work and
manage our context. And then we have our
skills, our packaged up workflows. Like
this is how we want our coding agent to
do planning. Here's how we want it to
implement. What's the procedure we want
it to work itself through based on the
input we give it for what we want to
build. And I don't need to get into the
details for all six components here of
the AI layer. I have a video that I'll
link to right here where I really get
into all this. Just know that these are
the components we create to make our
coding agent understand our conventions
and process. We build these up and we
compose them together to create our full
workflow. And that is the system. And
so, I'll cover this diagram really
quickly because this is the flow, right?
Like we build up the AI layer, and now
here's how we use it. And so, we create
it at first. That's what this stage
represents for both green field or brown
field. We're either going to be building
up our initial rules and workflows from
the idea of what we want to create if
we're starting from scratch or if we're
working on top of an existing code base,
we're going to understand the code and
document it. We're going to document our
conventions, build up our workflows. And
then either way, it's going to converge
into the exact same process that I call
the R Piv Loop. This is how I build any
new feature or fix any bug in any code
base. And so I start by researching,
just exploring how we're going to be
tackling this problem. And then from
there, I do structured planning. And
again, I have rules and sub agents and
skills that drive this more higher-level
process. That is the system. So I create
a structured plan that has things like
my validation strategy and the task list
that I have for the agent. And like I
said earlier, when you are at level
three, which is what I recommend, you're
very much a part of the process here.
We're having the conversation with the
coding agent to establish things, having
it grill us with questions to remove
assumptions, and then we create that
final plan that we then send into
implementation. So we have another
skill, another workflow for it to
operate on that plan that we create. And
of course, we have a lot of validation
at the end. And so the system here for
how the coding agent can run unit tests
and even do full end-to-end testing. And
then human validation if you want to
really make sure that your reliability
is top-notch. So there you go. That is
the fastest I've ever blitzed through
helping you understand a full system for
AI coding. So I hope that makes sense at
a high level. We build the components
that create our harness, and then this
is the flow to leverage it. And I won't
talk about system evolution too much
here, but we also have the whole idea of
every single time your coding agent
makes a mistake, it's worth not just
patching it and moving on, but having
that conversation with your coding agent
to figure out what part of our AI layer
can we improve so that issue doesn't
happen again or at least it's less
likely to happen again. Like maybe
there's a workflow we can refine or a
new rule that we can add to address the
issue that the coding agent created. And
so going back to the article now, when
you get to level three, that's when you
really start to have the system that I
showed you just now very briefly. You
have for yourself or even as a team
standard the rules and skills,
everything in the AI layer, and then
you're composing that together in the
flow that I described. And so how
exactly you're going to with your coding
agent go through all the steps it takes
to go from idea to production or pull
request. And so when you do that system
evolution, every single R pivot, if
you're figuring out how can I make the
AI layer, how can I make my process
better over time, you'll start to get to
the point where when you have a new
request come in, you're like, "You know
what? I think my coding agent or I know
my coding agent is just going to knock
this out of the park." Like I don't even
really have to iterate on the plan. Or I
don't even think I have to validate
things besides a couple of quick spot
checks. When you get to that point,
that's when you know you can start to go
to level four and maybe even level five.
You start to sort of build that muscle
of what you can trust your system to
accomplish, you grow that muscle, you
grow that system over time, and you can
start to trust it with multiple tasks
operating through it autonomously.
That's level four. And then dark
factory, that's when you have to take
your system even beyond what I've showed
you. So last thing I want to cover here
is just talking about what goes into
really taking a system like I described
and turning it into a fully fledged dark
factory. So I found this article that
I'll link to in the description that I
think very nicely puts how you want to
build up a dark factory. What are all
the different components? Cuz like they
say right here, a dark factory isn't
just AI writes code. It's a system with
distinct components that handle
different stages of the development
pipeline. If we're going to go from
massive spec all the way to ship code,
we have to have a lot of different
agents operating to triage the different
tasks from the spec, to build each one
of them, to review the pull requests, to
manage the deployments, to do the
regression testing. There is so much
that goes into a dark factory. In fact,
I did quite a few live streams on my
YouTube channel. I'll link to one right
here where I built a dark factory live
and I used Arkon, my open source harness
builder, to create a lot of the
workflows to manage all these different
parts of the development pipeline and it
was a lot of work and there were still a
million things I needed to do to truly
make it reliable. It's just more of an
experiment that I did. I called it my
dark factory experiment. But anyway, it
starts with a planning agent. So, once
we have the larger spec distributed into
individual tasks, we need an agent to
handle the planning for that one task.
And so, it's just like what I showed you
in the system earlier where we want to
create that structured markdown
document, our plan of attack for that
specific feature or bug. And then, we
send that into the code generation
agent. So, we have a handoff there where
usually it's a markdown document is
passed to another agent to execute and
create that pull request. And then, the
validation layer to review that pull
request. It's important to not do your
code review in the same context window
where you do the implementation cuz
there's a lot of bias that's built up
there. And then, of course, we have the
deployment system. Again, no human in
the loop going straight into production.
So, we want an agent that manages that,
maybe doing things like regression
testing as well. And then, we need the
orchestration layer. We need that
higher-level agent to take the spec and
split it into tasks, to manage the
handoffs between the different agents
and make sure that we don't have
duplicate work or that one agent is
stalling waiting for inputs that are
never going to arrive. I mean, even just
reading through this, you can start to
imagine all of the complexities, the
millions of things that can go wrong
because agents can veer off of your
initial spec and have a ton of tasks
that don't make any sense. They can
stall waiting for a handoff from another
agent that crashed. If there's no human
in the loop, you risk that those
failures happening without much
visibility because the whole point of it
is you don't have to pay attention to
it. And so you really got to make sure
that things are reliable before you ever
get to this point. And building the
orchestration layer on top of your
existing system is also an engineering
effort of its own. So it's not even just
like get the system to a point where
it's reliable, it's get to the point
where it's reliable and then you have to
build the next layer on top of it. So it
is a lot of work to get here. So again,
the dark factory is the dream, but yes,
it takes a lot of engineering effort.
And if you want to read the rest of the
article, I would encourage you to do so.
A lot of good stuff here. And they cover
some things I've been working on with
Arkon as well. Like deterministic and
agentic nodes. Sometimes you need the
reasoning capability of an LLM for a
step in a workflow, but other times you
don't. And you can make it more reliable
by having some things that are handled
deterministically just with code. Like
formatting code, running a linter,
triggering a deployment, you don't
always need an LLM. And so that's one of
the things I have built into Arkon. It's
just the idea of engineering harnesses
to drive these things. Like what Stripe
did with Stripe Minions. And then they
also go into the different failure modes
that we talked about here, like
cascading failures. Evaluation gaming is
another really interesting one. These
are the things we have to engineer for
to make it so the dark factory is
realistic at all. And yes, it can be
kind of daunting when you look at
something like this and think about what
really goes into making it reliable, but
this is also the future of AI coding. We
already see companies that are starting
to engineer these things successfully,
and it's only going to get more
realistic as coding agents and LLMs get
more and more powerful. And so this is
something that I'm really leaning into
and I encourage you to do as well. I've
already done some experimentation with
it like I talked about earlier, and I do
want to do more content on building a
dark factory. So also let me know in the
comments if you'd be interested in that.
And so with that, that's all I got for
you today. If you appreciate this video
and you're looking forward to more
things on agentic engineering and maybe
dark factory building as well. I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next video.